good morning everyone
and welcome to this free the truth
seminar
um my name is deepa govinda raj and
driver
along with my colleague professor ian
monroe who's on the panel today
we're here to discuss and uh mark
the ninth year since the stratfor of the
global intelligence files were released
and um on our panel today we have
three fantastic um
panelists we have dr solid braifus who's
a tech researcher
and a whistleblowing expert
hi silas um we have john kiriakou who is
uh well known as the cia torture
whistleblower
and we have uh laurie laup who
um is well known as a hacktivist
and an expert on all things information
technology
and of course we have professor ian
monroe whistleblowing expert
and um founder co-founder of free the
truth
in terms of today's session
our this webinar is being
transmitted by on the dea channels as
well as
um by a number of other sources
we're also very grateful to consortium
news who are reporting on this event and
streaming it through their twitter
channel
um a big thank you to the committee to
defend julian assange whose grassroots
supporters have contributed towards the
cost of the zoom
uh and as they have done in ordinary
times outside of coping to the costs of
the hall that we used to vote
we have speakers today from across the
world across from australia to america
um and we're going to talk about issues
that
affect both the global south and the
global north
and um as we go into this one of the
things that
um that sticks in my head is mike pompeo
talking about wikileaks being a
hostile non-state intelligence service
and it seems quite apt that it was this
hostile non-state
intelligence service that was supposedly
betting the government of russia
that nine years ago um
through the ingenuity of people like
julian assange and
those who were behind wikileaks
brought to light the way in which a
private
unaccountable firm was um
essentially engaging in all kinds of
activity
including bribery and
um and manipulation
to uh and would it literally stop at
nothing
including uh in order to boost its
bottom line
so that it get information a privileged
commodity
that was only available to the few and
this was of course highly manipulated
tailored information and rather than
a rather than a source of knowledge and
information for the many which is what
wikileaks sought to do and wikileaks of
course did this
through being pioneering in offering
what was
an electronic dropbox so to speak for
whistleblowers that
provided anonymity both to the source
as well as to as well as a certain level
of security
for the documentation a level of
security that means that to this day
wikileaks has a 100 record of accuracy
um in in contrast what this private
intelligence firm stratfor was doing was
um providing information to governments
to
um to the marines to
lots of um quite
dubious uh regimes around the world
as well as to companies like dow
chemicals
and the for example with dao the they
were reporting
information in relation to activists
uh who were who were
reeling from the pogba gas tragedy in
india in madhya pradesh
where um you know so many people
over 500 000 people were injured as a
result of
a gas leak and i i always remember the
story of this particular
trade unionist a worker who
was carrying a gas called phosgene in a
container and
managed to drop it on himself and then
pulled off the mask
the gas mask that he was wearing and
died within 72 hours of inhaling
this information now not only was dao
involved in
this huge tragedy which went under the
union carbide
overhanging the company
but it also was involved in
contaminating the water after that
and um stratfor was also involved
involved in um in in relation to the
vancouver
olympics on advising coca-cola
about peta activists and what they were
involved in
so for those of you who are activists
sitting in the audience wondering what
julian assange's case has to do with you
a lot of what wikileaks revealed was
about the ways in which
governments and private actors were
colluding to
um to to essentially clamp down on
activism and whistleblowing on the
public
right to know now stratfor
uh quite uh interestingly describes
itself and i'm trying to read the words
here
as a as the world's leading geopolitical
intelligence platform
um and this geo world leading
geopolitical
intelligence platform is actually trying
to make money for a small bunch of
shareholders
and it is actually public money that is
being used in the pursuit of many of the
activities that um stratfor is trying to
get into which is
quite to a large extent disconnected
from the socio-political and economic
realities of the jurisdictions in which
companies like stratfor
operate um in a way what they do
is entrench some of the structural
inequalities including racism
that that comes from the kinds of
perverted information that is leaked in
relation to some of these sources
and when governments and intelligence
agencies and public bodies
rely on this kind of information which
is flawed
biased and often inaccurate
and where the customers of this
information within these governments
often become assets often become people
who work within
intelligence firms like stratfor
it creates a situation where the uh
the people who are using these inform
this information or the people who are
providing this information
are largely unaccountable to the
ordinary public while benefiting hugely
from public money and this is something
that
many of you especially those of you who
are interested in
uh holding the state accountable for its
criminality will be really interested in
so i'd like to um stop there and
invite our first speaker john kiriyaku
to tell us a little bit about what for
those of us who don't know very much
about what firms like stratfor do
could you tell us about who they are
what they do what their kinds of clients
are
and how this affects um you know the the
quality of the intelligence that we get
over to you john certainly thank you
thanks for having me first
uh first off i i'm very happy to talk
about stratfor
uh because i think it's a very important
issue that most people
uh don't talk about it's certainly an
issue here in washington
um and i've always gotten a little bit
of a kick out of
the conversation about stratfor because
i never took stratfor seriously as
a serious organization and frankly i
don't know
any intelligence professional uh that
did or that does
stratfor the the joke about stratfor for
many years has been
uh about stratfor's so-called
secret sources they talk about what a
great
intelligence platform they are because
they have these sources
all over town well the joke is that
their sources
are the press officers of every
uh embassy in the city and
and their other special sources are the
washington post and the new york times
so really what stratfor is what stratfor
has always been
is a group of um underpaid
very attractive young women and we can
talk about that separately if you'd like
because that's who george friedman the
the co-founder of stratfor
always hired was very attractive young
women
um sitting around and reading newspapers
and uh watching cnn and msnbc
and jotting down notes and then calling
the embassy of yemen or the embassy of
saudi arabia the embassy of jordan
and talking to the press officer there
and then writing up a report like it's
some special
secret insight that nobody else could
possibly come to
um and that's why when jeremy hammond
god bless him
uh did what he did i was so
shocked at the way the boom was lowered
on him
because he didn't reveal anything he
didn't reveal anything that was
dangerous what he did though was
expose a very washington kind of
phoniness that uh
that was stratfor and its business model
now what firms like stratfor
try to do what they try to market
is a certain level of
political and strategic insight that
nobody else has
uh what they say is that they're full of
former cia people former nsa people
former fbi people
that's just simply not true they can't
afford those people
so they hire these young college
graduates
um researchers uh writers
to just press pieces and
send out their bulletins
mostly their subscribers were
individuals now they brag or they used
to brag on their website about how their
subscribers were mostly fortune 500
companies that was largely not true
they were mostly individuals llc's
sole proprietorships with very specific
questions
should i do business in yemen should i
buy that
that silver mine in romania
and then you would need to know things
like well if i do want to buy that
silver mine in romania
uh who's going to win the next election
the conservatives who are going to let
me mine the silver
or the socialists who are going to not
let me mine the silver
and that's it this was all about this
was all about
capitalism it was all about making money
it wasn't about strategic thinking it
wasn't about
long-term prognostication it wasn't
about
secret clandestine sources this was all
money and that's why stratfor didn't pay
its people anything
because it was all about money for the
principles and putting money into the
pockets
of those people who had negotiated
favorable terms with the government and
with other investors
so in my view
stratfor has always just been
a fake phony
underachieving organization
whose sole purpose was to make money for
its initial investors
it provided nothing to the greater
context of intelligence collection
or intelligence analysis in washington
or even in the business community
thanks john can i just stay with you
there and ask you to tell us a little
bit about
how um organizations like stratfor if
they are
you know i i heard somebody describe
them as
half clown half intelligence agency
and i was really curious if if they are
indeed
who who as described
why is it that they are so powerful
could you tell us a little bit about
that and also about your
general understanding of how their
information is used by organizations
within
the establishment um in addition to
you know in addition to furthering
the interests of capitalists sure
let me answer your your uh second
question
first the information um is used by
insiders to
to either confirm or to refute the
information that the insiders have
because their sourcing is going to be
different um insiders you know at the
cia we had this mantra
and it was uh recruit spies to steal
secrets
period that's how you get promoted by
recruiting spies to steal
secrets um stratfor doesn't recruit
spies to steal secrets that's espionage
and they don't have diplomatic immunity
or diplomatic cover
to protect themselves so they don't
steal the secrets
they just read the papers and analyze uh
the the media and see if the if the
results
are the same as what the the
intelligence organizations are uh
are getting in their own analysis so
that's easy
it's just to either refute or to support
uh conclusions based on different
sourcing
uh how did they get started well you
know
every retiring or former cia officer
especially from the directorate of
intelligence which is the analytic
organization inside the cia
wants to keep doing what he's doing see
at the cia part of the culture
is to convince you that your job is so
specialized that you can't do anything
else
right you can't market that skill
outside the cia
and that's one of the reasons why
turnover is so low at the cia it's
actually under two percent
and has been for decades uh it's because
they convince you that you can't do
anything else where are you going to go
you're going to go to the washington
post you can't because then everything
that you write has to be cleared by the
cia you can you'll never get anything
published
so what you do if you do leave the cia
is you
create an organization like stratfor or
join an organization like stratfor
which is trying to do exactly what the
cia has always been doing but without
the sourcing
so like i say it's it's an empty shell
of of what a real intelligence
organization
uh would do thanks john
uh lowry thank you very much for being
here
um could you tell us a little bit a lot
of what we're talking about in relation
to the stratfor leagues
also has a a lot to do
with um the work done by anonymous
uh could you tell us a little bit about
the hacktivism that sits
alongside um these leaks and what
what the people who were involved and
what the circumstances that were
surrounding this were about
uh larry you're still muted i'm just
going to make sure you're unmuted
sorry um yeah i can try and fill in a
little bit of those blanks um
unfortunately the passage of time and
the several
assaults on my um brain made it harder
to remember the exact details but um
yeah the the way um stratfor came into
my radar as an
online activist um exploring how to do
activism
online um the modalities of activism
and the emergence of anonymous as this
kind of network
decentralized chaotic actor
the internet developing a conscience and
trying to um
exert the power of the network to try
and make the world a better place and
it came on our radar because um we we
found out that there was a dirty tricks
campaign against us and
not just us um a dirty tricks campaign
against
um online activists against wikileaks
against uh glenn
glenn greenwald and some other
journalists who were reporting on
information
and that was coming out of online
activities and this um
this idea that this was something that
could be solved
i am the right kind of strategic
uh interventions and um
so stratfor um
we're indicated with hp gary and
palantir
and some other of these private sector
intelligence um adjuncts
should we say um in attempting to
disrupt these activities
similarly to how you mentioned earlier
deeper the um
um activism uh to do with the uh
the the chemical uh atrocities um
in india and attempts to um kind of
uh nail nail that activism and control
it
and similar thing was uh was um being
perpetrated against this
new emergent and tendency of online
protest
and um you know as john said the these
these were not professionals these are
you know cowboys in a clown car um
selling um lisa simpson's magic rock
that makes the tigers go away and you
know you don't see any tigers here so
the rock must work
and then you can get away with this
because if you claim to just have a
little bit of intelligence then maybe a
few law firms or a few other firms are
going to hedge their bets
because they just want to you know
potentially get that bit of intelligence
before making the wrong
business decision et cetera in some part
of the world that they don't have
full insight into but um
the the the actual activities that were
exposed were
and yeah i mean it's to say that they
were they were not contributing to
strategic analysis or or and
prognostication or planning is too
diplomatic they
they were people trying to make a quick
buck
by being the cyber version of the
pinkertons you know
and some i jump to the state that can
come in and and throw a little muscle
around and act very unprofessionally and
try and ensure
things go the way that they ought to go
thanks laurie while we're with you could
you tell us a little bit about what
motivates
the kinds of people who get involved and
anonymous and
who are who are seeking to
reveal such information before we go on
to solet to talk a little bit about
how that differs from whistleblowing or
how that is similar to whistleblowing so
um are you able to tell us a little bit
about anonymous and
what what kinds of uh people get
involved why they get involved
what what motivates them what kind of
act um
activism they're involved in etc i mean
speaking solely
through the lens of my own perspective
and my own experiences
and the the emergence of this
um entity anonymous or this
collective dynamic of people on the
internet and
was a liberating and empowering um
pivotal change in how people that were
on the internet or so some
small subsection of them were able to
view their ability to relate to the
world and it's not just
a place that you go to escape these
things that you you were never really
particularly uh on board with but it's a
means
by which you can actually um
envision a better world and try and
bring it about and it was um it was
vastly liberating even um
small symbolic uh gestural token actions
such as helping
um protesters out who were being
suppressed by authoritarian regimes
or revealing information about them
corporate and civic
uh malfeasance in in office and
it it suddenly became apparent that
there was a
power here for a large number of people
collaboratively
to exercise a a form of
oversight i would say that that hadn't
emerged previously
and and we were playing around with that
role and what what our ability
um could be to to to um
to agitate for justice in that diversity
thanks laurie um i i i wonder if we
could now move to select
to talk to you a little bit about um
what what it means to hold power to
account and how whistleblowers do that
and where the boundaries lie between
um those who are outside the
organization and those who are inside
the organization when they whistle blow
and also perhaps also talk a little bit
about
um how this relates to the case of
julian assange and
um the current situation in relation to
how um the state is going after him so
over to you sualet um
so it's interesting i mean we had this
anniversary on the
february 27th 2012 wikileaks began
publishing the
you know global intelligence files of
over five million emails
uh from the texas headquarters of this
company
um and uh and the emails were from 2004
to december 2011
and this this act was one of a number of
acts
in the activities of wikileaks that have
really
helped um expand the definition of
whistleblower
so traditionally um whistleblower has
sort of evolved really from the 1980s
and 1990s as being primarily about
employees
revealing serious wrongdoing often fraud
financial fraud
from inside a company but what we've
seen is
a movement over the last decade and
wikileaks was certainly a major
causative factor in this
to broadening that definition and and
that now includes
in many definitions many protections
contractors
subcontractors it's now been expanded to
say
volunteer board members of a church or
school
and so these are people who are not just
employed by or subjugated if you will by
a boss in the organization
but have some role in that community uh
increasingly i've seen debate
in academic circles about whether or not
university students
might be considered whistleblowers by
virtue of being inside a university
community even though they don't hold a
official role as an employee or an
oversight person like a board manager
for those people who are entirely
outside of a community and
again the lines of community blur in an
electronic setting
but for those people who are outside
entirely outside of an organization
the term that i and some other academics
have used
to describe uh people who reveal serious
wrongdoing is
is bell ringers and uh bell ringers
and particularly public interest
bellringers which i think
you would say this uh the people who
provided this
information to wikileaks as a publisher
to publish or acting in the public
interest
um and we can talk about what it's
revealed in the public interest
um both of those sorts of people need
protections
and particularly one of the things that
they need protection from
is a kind of ugly threat that's been
emerging
from the onward push towards better
protection for whistleblowers
and so that better protection has been
exemplified by
a huge growth over the last decade
in the number of laws and
implementations of policy that protect
whistleblowers including
by the end of 2021
some 27 countries in the european union
who will all have to adopt
a minimum standard set of laws in
national transposition of the eu
directive protecting whistleblowers this
is a
massive thing it's fantastic um
so uh so why you know why is this
important well you've seen this
move but there are threats to this move
and one of
the you know threats to it is a risk
that with suppliers and we've seen this
in julian assange's case
and in other cases will be charged with
data misuse or
unauthorized access of data charges
and and that this will be the side door
channel that is used to attack the
whistleblower or
uh or someone who reveals the you know
makes a disclosure in the public
interest
well why is that um okay it's because
most things are actually stored in
electronic form these days
and they're you know we aren't reverting
to paper very much
and so a lot of the computer misuse
acts um internationally have a very
broad scope
uh and they basically refer to either
using any telecommunications uh you know
facility well we all use those every day
they follow us around like tracking
devices with our phones
um you know or or any online uh
technology or any data that's stored in
a technological
um basis so that you know that is a
that's a pretty serious concern um uh
that's a threat to to the whistleblower
and the kind of general movement
that happened from 2010 to now and that
is a push towards more transparency
so i think one thing that's really
important about the role of public
interest bellringers as well as
whistleblowers
and this is an emerging thing that has
happened uh really over the last
decade to 15 years is that um
we once in our in our free and open
democracies believed that
uh transparency was a corrective
mechanism in its own right
so you have foi laws for example and
freedom of the press
and that's great but we're drowning in
data right we have more data i can't
even keep all the files straight on my
computer you know
let alone all the other data that's on
the internet we are drowning in data
which is probably why some people pay a
lot of money to places like stratfor
um the problem with that is that
what's in short supply now is less the
data and more
the guides and the signposts and the
guides and the signposts are incredibly
important
those that do so in the public interest
are doubly so and so
punishing the whistleblower um or
punishing the public interest
um bellringer is is taking away
that kind of key junction in the process
that you need to have a protective
umbrella over
in the public interest and that process
looks like the whistleblower
the public interest bell ringer to
for example the journalist to the
publisher to the public
if you break down any element of that
chain the
the people who lose are the public uh
and and and we've seen you know for
example um you know significant
whistleblowing case uh alton deltor's uh
case the luxely case you know he was
initially charged with
a computer is going to be charged with a
computer crimes related
charge and this is not um unusual at all
so so i think those those that's where
we've got a kind of nexus point that's
very relevant
to to this case um and
uh i might just add that in terms of
some big
headline observations about why this
case
uh is so important um i mean the clown's
comment is quite funny
uh you could you could make an
observation that um stratfor
uh you know we thought that they were
opening to the cia as john said but
really they were sitting in the just
doing google searches all day long
um and it is john and it's not only a
question the cia has access to
information that obviously they don't
have but
cia actually does operations they don't
just do google searches right
so so um and that's really i mean you
could say that's the difference as well
between i don't know blackwater and the
economist
um so i think there was the atlantic
might have quoted someone at the time
that the stratfor
uh uh documents were published saying
something like um
what you got in the intelligence reports
from stratfor is what you could have
gotten from the economist uh the week
before
um you know and uh and i think
you know the observations that stratfor
has paid sources which came out of this
is interesting because i think i believe
the atlantic
also said uh yes we have people like
that they're called reporters
um and but the difference is their
reports go to the public
um so the that those are kind of my
observations on
on this thank you sulet
um thank you very much um i'd i'd
just like to move very briefly if i made
to introduce
professor ian mundro who's one of the
co-founders of
free the truth and to ask if ian would
you like to
add to this discussion of whistleblowing
because you are a
highly regarded whistleblowing expert
and i wondered whether you wanted to add
to
uh the comments suelet has just made
before we go to questions just to warn
everybody who's watching in the audience
if you wouldn't mind
uh posting your questions if you're on
the zoom if you can post it within the q
a tab
then we can pick it up for i can pick it
up for the speakers and if you're
watching on one of the um
other channels at our expert our tech
experts
who are beavering behind the scenes will
post them back to me so hopefully we
will capture many of the questions that
you want to ask
so if you can please post your questions
now while ian is speaking then we can
try and pass them out to the right
speakers
ian over to you thanks deeper and uh
thanks very much
for the speakers and their very valuable
insights into
the stratfor leaks and more generally
into the role of
uh these uh private security in inverted
commerce or private intelligence firms
regardless of their competence
and of course if you read the global
intelligence files or some of them
uh they're riven with prejudice uh
mistakes
and of course um yeah basic errors
all coming probably from the newspapers
that they're reading i suspect rather
than
intelligence work as this has been
pointed out already
uh and i would i would like to i
completely agree what sulet just said
uh if you think of the whistleblower
chelsea manning she was
uh charged with a whole bunch of things
but she was actually only convicted of
computer fraud and misuse i think it was
three counts um five counts
and put in prison for 35 years and that
what they do if
what the judge did in that case was of
course
give the maximum possible sentence uh
for a
relatively mundane what apparently
mundane
crime because they couldn't uh convict
her of anything else because he
also he'd done the public interest
disclosures he'd revealed
the existence of war crimes in
afghanistan
and iraq and um julian assange of course
is being prosecuted
more or less the same thing uh using uh
based on similar laws
except he's being even though he wasn't
the whistleblower he was the
uh po the published the journalist who
handled the disclosures
chelsea madness discloses he's up for
175 years
and of course it's um as many people
have
already pointed out this is uh
criminalization
or not only of whistleblowing but
we on the one hand we've got these new
whistleblower laws being created for
whistleblower protection which is all
great
but on the other hand we've got other
other laws being
used or misused uh for
very severely um to try and deter
whistleblowers and also whistleblower
journalists
and uh people who support whistleblowers
but um yeah i think it's a
very serious problem not just amongst
the whistleblowing problem that the
community but also in the
activist community more generally i
think last year or the year before last
amnesty international produced a major
report
on the role of uh private intelligence
firms that were tracking activists its
activists and uh
i think they particularly focused on a
film called the nso
but this is obviously a growing problem
and i remember as well as wikileaks um
i remember um mr um
robert tibbo raising the issue that
activists were being tracked by the
intelligence community as well
um journalists and so on in uh he gave
the example of a police whistleblower in
in canada um and
the journalist was being was asked by
the
um canadian police force to can can you
get information on
on this on the journalist so we can find
out who our who the whistleblower is
but uh yeah i think that um this is a
serious problem i just want to
um even though the companies that we're
strapped for may be
uh clownish and not particularly
professional or um
if you look at uc global of course
that's that was that seems to have had
much more of a an effect as it were in
the sense
that it seems to be have had more
very close links with us intelligence
and also with um the type of information
surveying lawyers uh journalists
whistleblowers anyone talking to
wikileaks staff
and also possibly um providing
information or misinformation
which is then being circulated in the uh
within the media but i i was just
wondering what in
in i would like to ask the question of
the speakers what do you do about
it um how do you uh in the it wasn't
brilliant in the hp gary case anonymous
basically revealed
um how incompetent hb gary was and that
this led to a
decline in its reputation and its
insolvency
but how do we deal with this how do we
address this uh this issue does anyone
have
any speakers have any particular um
i could i could jump in at this point
um i i think we actually ought to take
seriously
mike pompeo's um suggestion of what the
world needs and that that is
a public intelligence agency that is not
beholden
to the partisan interests of a
particular region
or a particular corporation or a
particular demographic
um but is beholden to the interests of
humanity
at large and the reason we need to have
a public distributed decentralized
intelligence agency is because as soon
said our grievous
our responsibility our duty um to act as
the overseers of power um
which is uh of um you know
in inestimable importance for a civic
society it's the reason we have
a court in public is the reason why the
the king
deliberates at the court in public it's
the reason why the administration of law
is done in public it's the reason why
democracy is done
transparently and publicly as far as
possible
and that's because power when it is not
uh under oversight that is effective
uh tends inevitably towards corruption
um and
uh unpleasant things happen and the
problem is
we it's not a lack of information that
we have it's a lack of
ability to analyze that information and
understand the import
and so we need to need to bootstrap the
um structures so that the
public can continue to to to
see what is being done um with the power
that is seeded
you must remember this that all power is
seeded by the public to governments and
to private corporate entities etc
and to ensure that they are not um
crossing
some lines in the sand that we should
you know uh
retain the right to draw and i think
we've lost that and as we transfer into
this digital age we we have to
think to ourselves very carefully how do
we continue to
uh have that uh faculty to
exercise that oversight and for that we
need um
entities like wikileaks but it's not
just the ability to source
documents and to to get to office source
protections and to publish them without
fear or favor
but it's also meaningful analysis
and implications and and so this speaks
to
the way that um whistleblowing and bell
ringing into that fantastic
extension of that analogy um become now
an integral
part of the role of journalism in
society that
it's inextricable it's not no longer
just this um
uh separate class of journalists whose
job it is to report on the news but
anyone in any position where they
interact with a system
where some information about the inner
workings of that system is necessary to
be known by the greater
greater whole and now puts on the hat
of that that that duty to disclose
and we need to make it as frictionless
um we to eliminate all the barriers of
entry to do that we need to make it
safe and we need to make it effective
because without that
and power will continue to tend towards
um tyranny thanks laurie
um there are a couple of questions which
are surfacing in the chat and before we
um go into that what one of the things
that it's worth probably
picking up is a question about um julian
and
the way you know lowry talked about
holding power to account and
um how a democracy works and how it
should be transparent and how we should
understand that the
the justice system works in a reasonable
way and i'd like to
go to sulet and lowry
to talk to them a little bit about um so
could you tell us about
how this timeline of the stratfor leak
sits with
the broader timeline of julian's
indictments and particularly could you
focus on
the way the the superseding
enlightenments were introduced and
explained that a little bit to us
because i think a lot of people don't
understand
um the problems with due process not
just in terms of companies like stratfor
um planning to hold whole julian as
one of the as some of the leaks revealed
as a keep him as a bride in prison move
him from country to country
and so to talk about these things but
then also perhaps go to larry and talk
about a little bit about
what the extradition process feels like
so because although this
um webinar is essentially commemorating
the stratfor leaks i think we have to
also talk about the
organization and the people who were
involved in
um in
bringing the information that was of
public interest to light
and how much many of them have lost and
have sacrificed
in order for us to be able to know
what's really going on
whereas the people who are the war
criminals the bush
the bushes the blairs the um
the obamas of this world are putting out
new books and
sitting free and enjoying their lives so
i think we do have to talk about
what's happening in julian's case and
what's happening um
in belmarsh prison where julian you know
he's been given his warm clothes in
october
or rather they've been sent into him and
yet the prison hasn't delivered them to
him and he's been sitting
freezing cold preparing for the trial of
his life and
um this really brings a sense of urgency
to our discussion
so over to you sulet if you can tell us
a little bit about
the second superseding indictment and
the broader timeline and then we'll go
to lowry about the extradition process
yeah i mean um so you know julian is
dragged out
of uh the embassy there are initial
charges laid against him in april 2019.
um and this has been due to a change of
government
uh in ecuador and the u.s activity
actively lobbying
ecuador and being instrumental in in
raising billions of dollars of loans
uh to ecuador um uh
with i think you know one of the price
tags being julian assange
so in late may 2019 the
you know espionage act charges are
unveiled against julian
and normally when those charges are uh
unveiled that's that's the last word and
that's because
um the uk as the kind of men in the
middle of all this
has to go through a set of processes to
start this proceeding because he's not
being tried for these crimes in the uk
he's
being you know the debate is one of
extradition not whether or not he's
guilty of those particular crimes this
time
so the hearing opens itself in february
2020.
um and uh that's because the us is
pushing to speed things up they want
things to happen quickly
um and you know there are a set of
hearings that are held
and then in june 2020 june 24
all of a sudden the u.s is like well
actually we've got additional charges
that we want laid
and the charge sheet is superseding
hence the names to preceding indictment
um the previous charges so it replaces
the previous
indictment now this is so confusing to
the process
and probably unprecedented uh in the
um uk extradition proceedings that have
gone before
for anyone certainly in my knowledge i
don't know of any case
what this has been done sort of halfway
through when the the cake is half baked
um uh that the uk
is is flounding around for four to six
weeks
after this has happened um uh because
they don't know what to do with it
they're not sure how to process it
it's actually a very um outrageous thing
for the usd
doj to have done at that time um and
and at the time these these superseding
indictment
this list of new charges uh are just
kind of
plonked on the um website of the doj
no articles no fanfare just one day it
kind of appears
who knows possibly that was how the the
uk government learned about it we don't
know
but um it you know from then september
there is uh the hearing and uh julian
assange's you know
formally readdressed and you know on
these new charges
now you just wouldn't normally do that
it's not it's not normal behavior
and he's now not having the opportunity
to respond
properly to a set of these new charges
which is
completely outrageous in the justice
system where he's about to be
extradited so not having the challenge
not having the opportunity to challenge
these new allegations
is is really an abuse of process um
uh but um that's what has gone
on here it's possible that um
the judge took a very dim view of this
uh in a sense it's an insult to the
british
justice system i i don't think you could
describe it as anything else it treats
the british justice system with a kind
of contempt
and and i suspect that most british
judges would take a dim view
of that um so uh
so that's that's where you know that's
where his case is you know is that at
the moment obviously
the um biden administration has decided
to appeal the finding
of the lower court which uh had what
many
people in civil society would would
argue is a very bad
set of decisions for freedom of the
press
and freedom of expression uh and human
rights
right up until the point in the decision
where the judge rules
not to extradite him but really on the
grounds of
uh of his mental health so um you know
i'm not ruling i'm not saying
he's not bad but he's mad and therefore
we won't extradite him you know it's
it's kind of smeared
um but at least he's not extradited but
uh the us didn't have to actually
um fight those they could have just said
it's gonna be a hard
fight on legal grounds and therefore
it's a waste of taxpayers taxpayers
monies
and by the way we have a whole new
administration do we really want to
spend the next years chasing the ghosts
of the last
four years administration and so they
could have just
decided to not proceed with that instead
they have
decided to do so so it will be
interesting to see
um what happens i think one of the
important things that has come
out of julian's case but it's also come
out of
um you know the other cases related to
it for example jeremy hammond's case
um chelsea manning's case uh
is a is the biggest kind of existential
threat
to the nature of investigative
journalism that we've seen in a long
time
and that threat looks like this where
you have
a journalist who finds information
a tip off that there is serious
wrongdoing that is happening
it may be illegal uh it may be just
immoral it may offend the public mores
and they ask for the disclosure of that
information whether it's a public
interest bell ringer or a whistleblower
for some evidence in in support of that
allegation there is a tilt
in the kinds of charges that have been
um laid against
the people involved in this you know
decade-long saga
and that tilt is to ask for that
evidence
is becoming a criminalized act
it is criminalizing the act of
verification and it's very ironic
because many politicians around the
world stand on their soapbox
and say oh my god it's terrible you know
facebook publishes fake news it's awful
awful awful
but here you actually have something
that will undermine the verification of
the accuracy of news in reporting
but it creates a terrible precedent it's
bad for the whistleblower
and integrity in society in the
organization and it's bad for journalism
uh and the last thing you want to have
is journalists who don't ask for
evidence
because then they're going to print
things that are simply wrong
i i think we saw some of that when um
either because of
journalists who choose not to ask for
evidence or journalists who
view the evidence only through a
particular lens when they are for
example embedded journalists doing war
journalism
and um like the journalist who was a
bullitt's a price-winning journalist who
was unwilling to reveal what happened
within the collateral murder with video
until
wikileaks revealed it and chelsea's
testimony came through
and it became more and more evident that
he knew about this information so
um yes it is it is really worrying isn't
it to see how
evidence gathering and the the process
by which
we can penetrate some of the um
the complexity and the opacity of these
kinds of
very complex institutions which make
very important decisions about our lives
and yet
we have very little control over and
where individuals in these institutions
are hiding behind
these facades to essentially um
enrich themselves whether it is
shareholders or stratfor
or whether it is the owners of uh
organizations such as these who are
um who are hiring intelligence
people who are sitting within the
establishment to then come over and make
money for themselves
but just to take a step back before we
go into
uh perhaps with you a little bit john uh
in a second
about how companies like stratfor smear
people and
what kinds of information the the leaks
actually revealed
um could i come back to lowry and what i
wanted to talk about this idea of
holding power to account and
um we we saw on the screen flashing by
for those of you who are watching the
live stream
the information provided by declassified
uk which
showed that there are serious questions
about conflicts of interest in relation
to lady emma r buttsnot who's the chief
who was the chief magistrate at
westminster magistrates court
and um how you know her son is involved
with a company called dark trace which
seeks to
shut down places like wikileaks how her
husband has a
um has a is partnering with
richard dear love in relation to things
and
how she herself receives financial
benefits from secretive partner
organizations of the uk foreign office
and you know looking at that and looking
at
for example a judge uh at a hearing
where
julian is called in front of the court
he says his name and his date of birth
and the judge brands him a narcissist
what does it feel like to go through
this extradition process particularly if
you are somebody perhaps on the um
autism spectrum who is um
expecting certainty my understanding
from the work of professor niels meltzer
the un special rapporteur
who has confirmed that julian was being
exposed to psychological torture
is that a big part of psychological
torture is the arbitrariness of the
process
and also the um
the inability to rely on institutions
that are supposed to protect you for
example in julian's case
he thought asylum he was granted asylum
and then
without grounds his citizenship was
revoked
and without due process similarly um you
know when he goes to the court
everybody else gets treated a certain
way he gets treated differently when he
in fact the law has to be changed after
the case is
taken in julian's case in order to make
the european extradition warrants for
example
uh run in an appropriate way or whether
it is in relation to
um you know the the treatment as
westminster magistrates course and i say
this as somebody who was
a legal observer julian's hearings
and how how how difficult it was
to attend those hearings and how we were
intentionally kept out
of the process so that you you know the
the right of the public to know
as much as if it is a right of julian to
have
a an extradition hearing or
or a judicial process where uh the
public can understand what's going on in
his case was totally trampled over in
this case
so um i'd like to move back to lowry
please and talk to you a little bit
about
your experience of the extradition
process and
um what it feels like in terms of this
arbitrariness within the process please
over to you larry thank you diva um
yeah i mean if you haven't had the
um wonderful opportunity in your lives
yet to read trans kafka i i suggest you
do
um he wrote a book called the trial and
from that and some of his other writings
we have this adjective in the
english language kafkesque and kafks
basically means um
well how can you describe it it's a a
system
um of administration of so-called
justice or law that is um
that is arbitrary that is undermining
that is um
to some extent gaslighting the people
that are involved in it um
because of all the expectations that uh
things should
proceed a certain way that there should
be a sort of bare
fairness of their equality to it
and you see these evaporators you
participate in the system and
it can be small things such as when
you're put into westminster magistrates
court you are um
you're not allowed able to sit with
council you're not able to confer
with council and um help them represent
you
as is their brief this is their
responsibility and this is your right to
inform them
you're put in a little goldfish bowl um
effectively segregated from the rest of
the court
and presented to the court as a guilty
party
and then you know select reminded us
that trial is not to establish
guilt the the judges in an extradition
hearing should not
allow themselves to form an opinion
on the guilt of the or non-guilt of the
requested person
however we see that it colours their
decision-making
the way that the united states in
particular because of our unbalanced
extradition treaty with the us
is able to completely set the stage and
frame the narrative
and steal a march on the storytelling
by the way the um the allegations are
put together in the indictments that
form the extradition
uh request and then as a soulette said
they could
somehow late in the game just decide to
wipe that slave and put a whole bunch of
new things on there
and then the problem in an extradition
hearing is you don't have a right to
contest
any of these claims say that again for
the people at the back
you are sitting in a goldfish bowl in
the dark being
lied about by the most powerful
organization in the world the most
powerful entity in the world
indirectly the the sole remaining
superpower in the world
in front of a institution that in theory
um administers justice under truth
that administers justice under truth
that uh ensures the outcome
by ensuring truth to ensure that justice
is done
you said and you listen to people lie
about you and you can't even raise your
hand and say please miss
please lady not to impugn any of our
judiciary
in particular but please can these um
people i haven't met from another
country i've never been to stop
lying about me so that they can lock me
up in a small box for the rest of my
life because
that isn't the way i was raised to
believe court should work there should
be an adversarial process of contesting
evidence and
um an impartial
panel of people who are not part of the
establishment the same political entity
that is embroiled in the uh abuses of
power that you are bringing to light
and there should be that at least that
check and balance and all these things
are not there in the extradition process
so it is
a little bit like you're being served a
meal of justice but
there's no there's no nutrients in there
that's just um
there's just psychological torture and
it's not a pleasant
process to be put through and it this is
why it's so essential to
have the um
have other people involved not to to
um accept themselves as passive
observers but to actually participate
as you attempted to do deeper as a
observer legal observer in this process
and so many other fantastic
organizations around the world have
attempted to do to say
hold on a minute you can't you can't get
away with this like we
we we we are here to watch and ensure
that
what's done is right and every effort
has been made
um in uh julian's case
to um obstruct that oversight faculty
again
to to ensure that things can be done in
a twisted and underhanded way
um and you know it's not very
for for anyone and i can only speak from
my own experience but um
someone of my should we say personality
typology uh or someone who's in the kind
of
mold of mindset of viewing the world
that i have um
have very strong sense of innate justice
and what is right and then to be to be
put into that
you know what should be a sacred and
hallowed place for the administration of
that justice and to see
its integrity and its honor
besmirched by by the way that process is
not
put together and orchestrated to ensure
justice but put together an orchestrator
to assure a particular
outcome a political outcome and that
political outcome in this case is the
suppression
of the vital and necessary um
duty of journalists to report the truth
without fear without fear and favor we
say without fear and favor
and you cannot say that anyone who is
aspiring to be an investigative
journalist or is working at a
publication
in uh in the capacity of an editor
is not looking at this case and thinking
i know where the line is now
i i know how far i can go and not no not
any further before i i come under the
crosshairs
and i have um myself detained in various
forms extra legally for for decade
um subjected to a vile uh character
assassination campaign
um my life made into a sorted so popular
mockery um and and facing uh withering
away in a cell
for daring to give the public what the
public
needs to know about things like war
crimes and things like
abuses of power in in detention in
guantanamo
and of the things that we absolutely
must
be able to see so that we can
say no we could say this is not on
and so yeah i guess to summarize um
the extradition process is very very
very flawed
and it is a similar
it is a simulation of justice in the
sense of
borderland um it puts on all of the airs
it puts on all of the
um costumes and it goes through the
motions but when you're sitting there
you can see that it is not
uh bent towards the the the moral arc of
this process is not bent towards justice
as it should be
um and um you know that's harrowing and
and i i'm lucky um being
the first person um for whom extradition
to the united states was refused um
on on the grounds of the forum bar
and and that it would be unjust and
oppressive to put someone
um with any sort of mental uh physical
uh health complications in such a
barbaric system of detention
i was lucky to be able to be here and
speak speak to you about this
um but these situations haven't changed
the
the detention system is still barbaric
someone put in there
with any psychological difficulties will
not flourish they
they will expect to have degradation of
their physical and mental condition
um and an inability to provide
meaningful care to them
and so we we we're still
fighting that battle um in julian's case
um and i just want to implore everyone
to remember that it's like we're all in
this fight
we can all play a role we can all do
something
even if it's just letting the power know
that you are observing
so writing a letter turning up at court
um expressing opinion
sharing this discussing it with friends
and family and say well
this does concern me it does concern me
i want to live in a world where an
organization
and a person um takes great risk and
exercises great courage to help the
world
see what is being done in their name
with the power that they steed
with the money that they give to to the
state
and i want to live in a world where that
person is not crushed
mercilessly to set an example to others
that power should not be
held to account
that's so powerful laurie lowry and
i mean i having spoken to you a couple
of times i
um just moved by what what
you have sacrificed and how how deep
your sense of justice is and
what contribution you have made to the
world and being able to do this
and how much um how much you've been put
through
which is completely and so utterly wrong
and unjust
carrying on with this sense of barbarism
that you spoke about
julian if he is extradited to the united
states will face 175 years in
a maximum security prison
for those of you who don't know what it
feels like to be in
the alexandria detention center there is
a
clip available online which we will try
and uh
share through the chat of what it feels
like inside the prison but ins
essentially even at pre-trial stage this
is before
any guilt has been established
julian will be kept in a in a very small
cell and the us specializes in these
really strange terms for example
julian will be kept under special
administrative measures which
uh for anybody who's read the center for
constitutional rights
report on what they call the darkest
corner of the world special
administrative
measures are essentially ways in which
you are cut off
and your lawyers are cut off from
speaking to the rest of the world in
relation to your trial
you are also placed in administrative
segregation as they term it
um which is essentially solitary
confinement where you're in your cell 22
hours a day
which the un has clearly defined as a
form of torture
and as chelsea of course went through
this in fact she was placed in a cage
and at times was deprived of her
clothing and the
the horrendousness of the process
doesn't end there they also talk about
um you know one of the things that
really bothered me when i was listening
to the hearings
was the way in which firstly the the
the prosecution the cps talked about
mental health
and the way in which it was described
and most of this process has been around
you know described around julian
and his personality rather than in
relation to the way in which states are
stamping on
citizens but in relation to julian they
talked about you know
even the judge talked about his mental
health but actually this is not a case
of mental health but a case of mental
injury
caused by five states stamping on his
head
collectively and repeatedly over a
period of a decade
and it's also about um how in julian's
case
um you know the the way in which in that
court
the united states was trying to pretend
as though
the u.s prison system is going to be a
holiday where julian will have career
development courses
in relation to what he could potentially
you know he would have
access to this particular tv channel
which would train him to
think about what he could do once he was
released from prison or how to
improve his uh personal skills which of
course you know
um no no no um
criticism of prison education but this
was
um in fact it was worse than any
re-education camp you can imagine in
some of the worst dictatorships and um
i know john uh in in terms of your
sacrifice you have been
through the us prison system yourself
and um
experienced its brutality as has uh
mumia abu jamal whom
we heard from last week and on the
assange defense
um webinar but also
as have the guantanamo prisoners many of
whom have died in guantanamo without
charge and we're never getting due
process
including children who were uh you know
um arrested when they were 14 and then
committed suicide when they were 21
while still inside guantanamo
so the us prison system isn't known for
um
it's its excessive kindness or its uh
superiority
in fact the the rate of suicides in in
the
prison population and particularly those
under uh these extreme solitary
confinement measures
is extremely high compared to um
i mean but what else can you do if
you're faced with 175 years
where the you know at least at the cps
he seemed to
keep suggesting they would do everything
to keep him alive so they can make sure
he goes through the 100
years whatever or is left of his life so
uh could i move to you john uh after
getting off that soapbox about how
this is and could you tell us a little
bit
where do i even begin
there are so many things that are
desperately
wrong with the us prison system first of
all everything that you said about
solitary confinement is true
the new york times did a uh
did an expose in the spring of 2016
on one of the maximum security prisons
in the state of california
and they talked about how the united
nations has determined that solitary
confinement for any
length of time beyond 15 days
is a form of torture well in the united
states
we we keep prisoners in solitary
confinement for as long as
44 years now imagine 44
years with no human contact this new
york times expose in california was
talking about
a solitary confinement system
where you literally have no
contact with any other human being when
you receive
mail for example you don't actually get
the mail
there's a computer monitor uh hanging
from the ceiling
of your cell of your six foot by ten
foot
cell out of reach so you can't damage it
in any way
they'll put your correspondence on the
screen
for five minutes you stand there and
read it and then
it's taken off and that's it
the only visitors you're allowed to have
are your attorneys
and even they are restricted to once a
month
you're allowed one phone call a month
it's monitored of course live you're
allowed
two showers a week your uh
your meals are provided to you through a
slot in the door
and you know when when we talk about
lock down for 23 hours a day and
exercise for one hour a day it's not
really exercising the conventional
uh definition of the term
every one of these cells and i know this
because i was in solitary confinement
but every one of these cells has a small
door at the back
and that door leads to a cage that's
outside
now the cage in my case was another six
by ten feet and so you can either walk
around in a circle or in an oval
in your indoor six by ten cell or one
hour a week i'm sorry one hour a day
go outside into the cage and walk in a
six by ten foot
circle that's enough to drive the sanest
man insane at this
california prison things got so
desperate that prisoners were smashing
windows and eating the broken glass
just so they could go outside for
medical care and speak to another human
being
that's what these these special
administrative measures are now there
are
there are sam units within prisons
and then there's a sam unit that is a
prison that's at the u.s penitentiary
at terre haute indiana where the
whistleblower uh
marty goddesfeld is currently being held
presumably if julian were to be
extradited and i think he will not be
he would go to the sam unit at terre
haute indiana
the thing with sam units especially at
terre haute
is the focus is to keep the prisoner
away from the media
it's all about communication you know i
was in this
modified sam unit at the uh at the u.s
prison
in loreto pennsylvania and
i was not permitted to file a freedom of
information act request
about myself that was a part of my plea
agreement
that i could never file a foia request
ever
ever again in my life and i thought to
myself one day you know these people are
so stupid
just by their nature they're just stupid
people because who else would work in a
prison than
a dum-dum uh that i decided to file a
foia request anyway
just to see if they would catch it and
they didn't catch it
and they actually responded to it quite
quickly most of what they sent me
was uh stupid stuff my own medical
records my own visitors list things like
that
but there were about a dozen pages that
were very interesting and very important
they were internal memos about how to
deal with me
and there was one that was very simple
and very important
and it was one page and it was written
in very large block
letters and it was from the warden to
all personnel in the prison and it said
caution inmate has access to the media
and that's really what the nature of
this
of this problem for them was that i had
access to the media
well julian is the media
and so imagine the links that they'll go
to
to silence julian now in my silly little
position
all i had to do uh was to smuggle
my i wrote a blog uh regularly called
letters from loretto that i i turned
into a book when i got home
but i i would just simply smuggle it out
with other prisoners
or i would smuggle it out through one of
my attorneys the whistleblower attorney
jessalyn radak
and it was easy enough marty goddesfeld
can't get anything out of that prison
and certainly if julian uh were in
the u.s penitentiary at terre haute they
would be on him like white on rice
as we stay here in the states he
wouldn't be able to communicate with
anybody but that's the point the point
isn't just to punish him
the point is to punish him and to
silence him
because when you silence him he can't
get that message out
and so people like us remain uninformed
we don't know what's going on we can't
push that message of truth and
transparency and openness
because we just don't have access to it
that's the point
now it we're lucky in the respect and
julian is lucky
in the respect that um
that the justice department is going to
have to
justify legally justify
its own prison system and it's
unjustifiable
and so i think that's where the victory
is for julian
i think the the us put itself in a
corner that it can't get out of
where they would have to convince the
the court of appeals
and perhaps the supreme court and
perhaps the european court of justice
that no there's nothing wrong with the
us prison system not only will
julian get a fair hearing in the united
states they'll argue
but when he's convicted and he will be
convicted because
you know the justice system isn't just
uh
in the u.s they'll lock him up in a
in a sam unit so for for
julian in the event that this that he's
not able to protect himself
and again i think that he will be uh the
fix is in
there's no justice here yep um
thanks john one of the things um that
was visible through
the hearings was the fact that julian
had been moved to the medical unit
at belmar not because they were
concerned seriously about his medical
health
although his medical condition was
serious in itself
they put him there to keep him out of
reach of the kinds of cameras that were
revealing for prisoners who had taken
footage of him which got revealed on
youtube
um within balmarsh so um talking about
segregating people in order to not
let them access the medias is not
something that is
that appears now to be unusual in
british prisons either
um could i now take um i'm trying to
draw in a couple of questions at a time
from the audience but one of the
questions that i think needs
a standalone answer is um could you give
us some quotes from the different
stratfor leagues and i'm i'm hoping that
sullette might be able to share some of
this with us
well yeah i mean um
the emails do provide some insight into
the psyche of the people in these
privatized um pseudo intelligence
providing firms
so one of the messages reads assange is
going to make a nice
bride in prison screw the terrorist
he'll be eating cat food forever unless
george soros hires him
and interestingly there's information
in some of the other ones that's quite
telling so one of them is reporting on
um him being arrested
and due to appear in a court in
westminster soon to face charges of rape
accused by two women in sweden quote
charges of sexual assault rarely are
passed through interpol red notices like
this one
so this is no doubt about trying to
disrupt wikileaks release of government
documents um and
and then they talk about you know
whether it could
disrupt the long-term viability um of
wikileaks
then there's a a sort of long discussion
between a set of people
um about uh whether or not
uh the the deaths in iraq are comparable
to pearl harbor
um and and they're actually putting
counts in the email well
there were you know pearl harbor had 2
400 you know and two military killed and
civilians killed whereas you know in or
the u.s fatalities in iraq
were 4 429 and 179
uk fatalities and and and the argument
that goes back and forth in this email
is
but it took and i'm quoting i'm so
excused by french
but it took years of [__] up to get
to that point in iraq
pearl pearl wasn't even a single day it
was a single morning
and and so the the mentality here
is it seems very at odds with what the
public
would think i was you know acceptable
about justifying um you know trying to
to stop a war it's like well
it took longer to kill all these
civilians and people in iraq and
therefore
it's not okay to actually um uh report
on it
another amusing entry was um
uh a comment really on how they view
i guess their clients um in washington
the foggy bottom bow ties
have their panties in a knot over
a specific iraq cable outed yesterday
not sure which one
may be yanked so that's a
clearly not not very complimentary
perspective they have
on the people who pay their bills um did
you have a couple of ones you wanted to
mention john sorry i didn't need to jump
in and cut you off
no actually i was going to talk about
some of the same things
uh you know it seems to me that
that these little embarrassing snippets
of information
that were released uh
were not as embarrassing to them as uh
as the fact that they lost all their
their customers credit card numbers
and they had to go back and apologize to
everybody
and they were they were embarrassed and
they were humiliated and they wanted to
take it out on
uh on jeremy hammond so you know
i should add to that that uh please do
one of the
one of the um companies whose credit
card numbers was leaked was the law firm
of
um the judge's husband the judge who
presided over jeremy hammond's um
criminal conviction so in in any barely
functioning
world she would have had to recuse
herself and and
it kind of just speaks to the fact that
it's such this incestuous relationship
between these um
entities and and the people that are
supposed to be you know
uh keeping an eye on them
thanks uh lowry could i just move back
to something we talked about with sullet
which is
the normalization of war that comes from
the use of intelligence agencies such as
this and what wikileaks did to kind of
bash through that barrier and uh remind
us about
you know we talk about black lives
matter but actually when
people have died in iraq and afghanistan
that doesn't seem to count
so um i wondered ian if you would like
to comment on some of the
normalization of war and how
whistleblowing and wikileaks
helps to um
help to surface that please thanks
deeper
yeah i think a really important aspect
of uh this particular case uh
if you look at stratfor the stratfor
leaks a lot of it some of its clients of
course
uh are big companies but a lot of them
are actually
military uh companies uh lockheed martin
uh
ready theon and so on and a lot of these
uh you know if you think of the
not just the military budget but the
intelligence budget a lot of it
is outsourced to uh private contractors
edward snowden for example was working
for a private contractor when he
blew the whistle on uh global mass
surveillance and
and so on and uh wikileaks itself
as uh lori has highlighted
it's a public it's a an intelligence
agency for the public it's a public
interest as it were intelligence agency
and that many of the whistleblowers who
were going to visit wikileaks were in
fact
members of the former
uk and u.s uh intelligence community
who who had blown the whistle on corrupt
actions
that they had witnessed uh such as mr
kiriakou and bravely come out and spoke
about this and then
and then got uh interested in the work
of wikileaks subsequently and i remember
um an event a few years ago which uh
jonkey riyaku
and um robert tibo and uh
craig murray all very courageous uh
whistleblowers and uh
and so on uh they talked about their own
circumstances but they made a
very big uh an important
uh message to the audience that the work
of wikileaks was vital even though their
cases were not necessarily directly
linked at that time
and i hadn't really made that that link
at that time just
it is a historic case because
as it's been mentioned before it's
related to
the criminalized you know if this
happens if this goes through julian's
sense gets prosecuted then this is the
end of journalism
because this is this is a this is a
journalist that was actually doing what
all the other newspapers weren't doing
and in in 2001 i think there was this
there has been a massive sea change in
global politics and
it's associated with the war on terror
and essentially it's the normalization
of war
uh i would i would i would describe it
as you just said and then that means
that um if you look at
the guardian for example which generally
does very good uh
articles about things like climate
change uh
gender discrimination and all sorts of
good stuff
but if you look at it you know it's
published so many
uh it's given a lot of time to tony
blair i think 75 articles
either interviews or basically press
releases
um since you know this guy this guy was
responsible for um
this whole way in which a very strange
man
president george w bush decided to go
and bomb a country
unrelated to 9 11 in response to 9 11.
and and since then there's been a whole
bunch of other
wars of a racist wars of aggression
against
overcome other countries and very few
journalists are challenging this but
wikileaks wikileaks
challenges this not only that it through
the work of whistleblowers
insiders who know what's going on it
reveals the dynamics
which other journalists for whatever
reason aren't doing
and i think this is it's a it's crucial
you know this this work is so vital not
just
for investigative journalism generally
but also for this
dreadful term from 2001 onwards
uh this sort of increased militarization
of the internet this this
this this general normalization of war
in the in the media
and people who call out uh you know are
concerned about
anti-war activists and human rights
activists they get tracked by these
companies they get smeared by these
private intelligence organizations they
get tracked surveyed by them
and they get that there's an attempt to
discredit and discredit them and again
julian the sans has become this
the center the absolute sort of
epicenter of this
this um this struggle and i think yeah
this this really isn't is
of historic importance basically this
case
thanks ian um can i just move back to
you john
to ask before i come round to all the
speakers for closing comments
to ask a question which has come from
the audience which is not actually a
question it's a comment
and um the the writer sends uh greetings
from the peace and neutrality island uh
alliance in ireland and says that
they as a civil servant as a former as a
retired civil servant they don't share
the general view about
whistleblowers and they have known cases
where whistleblowers made mistakes
um this particular individual knew the
mistaker and the mistake he as
he refers to him um the reason
he supports julian assange is because he
exposed criminal behavior by the us
government
and he he says that does require
exposure
but and this is the the controversial
but at least for me
is that in general i have reservations
about whistleblowing and i'd like to
bring in
john sullette and ian about that if i if
i may
um and if you could comment on that john
you know on on the the day that i met
jessalyn radak it was about four days
after my arrest
i i had read some quotes that jessalyn
had given to the
washington post and i had never met her
and i wanted to thank her for
supporting me in public so i called her
at something like six o'clock in the
morning i thought i would just leave a
message
and and she answered her phone and i
introduced myself and she said oh my
gosh i'm so sorry that you've been
arrested
why don't you come to my office and
let's meet so i went to her office a few
hours later
i was there for two hours and she agreed
to take my case and to help me
and on the way out i said to her i want
to thank you so much because
i know that you only represent
whistleblowers and i'm not a
whistleblower
and she said but you are a whistleblower
and i said no i'm not i
i'm just a regular guy who just
happened to see something that i
objected to
and and i i said something publicly and
she said
no whistleblower thinks he's a
whistleblower but there's a legal
definition
of whistleblowing and that is bringing
to light any evidence of waste
fuel sorry of waste fraud abuse
illegality or threats to the public
health
or public safety and she said that's
what you did
you're the poster boy for whistleblowing
well that was a revelation to me
and one of the other things that i
learned in this whole process is that
oftentimes
well most of the time whistleblowing is
not really a clean
process sometimes the whistleblower is
really
not a compelling figure it's somebody
who's hard to like
but that shouldn't matter all that
should matter is the information
that is revealed one of the other things
that i learned is motivation
for whistleblowing is irrelevant
all that's relevant is the information
does the information meet those
requirements
of exposing waste fraud abuse illegality
or threats to the public health or
public safety
once i understood that and accepted that
it was far easier for me to appreciate
what it was that so many different
whistleblowers around the world were
coming forward with
you don't have to like the whistleblower
you don't even have to agree with the
whistleblower
you just have to respect the information
thanks john um so election did you want
to come in on that or
um should we move to final comments
oh sorry ian would you like to go first
after you select oh i think i might just
sort of jump to
some final comments if i if i might um
and
and and it's a little bit upbeat in
this sense so one of the stratfor males
in the publication
wrote certainly the doj have a poster
case for a range of criminal indictments
to include the death penalty for assange
manning will be deep fried
uh i think it one of the other things
that comes out in these emails
uh is stratfor saying
we might we could maybe take the man
down
but it it may not be possible to kill
off this thing he's created
this wikileaks thing that he's created
and by that they meant not just the
organization but a way of thinking
um a new way of thinking and a new set
of actions
uh and i and i think that in a positive
sense
their fear was well founded uh and
that's because although julian
has spent more than seven years in one
form or another
in either prisons or um not having his
freedom
and under deep constraint in that time
we've seen things like italian
journalist
stephanie marazzi running a court case
around wikileaks related information
that was being sought through foi the
mid had been blocking just as a tactic
and took the matter to an upper court on
appeal and one overturning
a lower court's bad decision and that
resulted in
an important finding for all journalists
access to
information we've seen more than a
hundred
secure drop boxes rolled out around the
world
not just in support of anti-war
movements
or general reporting about corruption
but
protecting environmental crimes
protecting um covid uh related
i mean not crimes but you know fighting
environmental crimes
fighting uh coveted supply chain and uh
other crimes um immediate threat to
safety political corruption um
all sorts of of areas of both specialty
and field specialty and geography
um that that is now such a mainstream
idea that
it's it's de rigueur in most major
reputable media organizations that was
julian assange and wikileaks
they invented that um dozens of
countries around the world
have in the last decade adopted
whistleblower protection laws and
thousands of organizations have done so
often required by law including
uh first laws that applied federally
here in australia
in 2012 13 and then most recently in the
last two years
laws that apply to the private sector um
and
and then we'll see these 27 countries
rolled out by the end of 2021 across all
of the
eu with whistleblower protection laws
some of them such as in countries like
spain
where there has been literally no
stand-alone whistleblower protection law
anywhere
in spain in fact what we've seen is
improved cyber security for journalists
both in awareness of their own need for
cyber security
training that's offered through civil
society specialist education
universities reaching out to journalists
i set up training for
uh journalists in the master's program
at my university
and and a growing awareness that the
fact that the journalists not only have
to defend themselves
they've got to defend their sources when
it comes to the technology as well
and and a lot of information laid bare
so that the public is not only less
deceived but less trusting
of these information companies that are
linked to
the defense industry to the lies that
politicians may tell us
to get reelected in support of going to
war yet again
to cover up some financial or other
malfeasance
they would like the attention diverted
from and finally and most importantly
the profound change that has happened
over the last decade
whereby whistleblower is no longer a
dirty word
it is no longer a dibby dauber it is no
longer a rat
it is actually a justice seeker you know
and
increasingly uh i'm i make the argument
and i hear it
reflected back in what people are saying
that whistleblowing is seen as
an emerging type of human right within
the freedom of expression right that we
have
um uh declaration of human rights it is
the right to dissent
from wrongdoing it's a right that was
established not for whistleblowers per
se but for people as a whole
after world war ii in europe when we
decided that no it was not okay
to just stand by and say i didn't say
anything about what i saw that was
happening that was so awful
no that wasn't acceptable say the courts
say the people
and and now we see this translated into
a different mentality in how
whistleblowers are viewed
and i think that wikileaks and indeed
these uh these publications as a part of
wikileaks's activities have played a
role in that transition in all of those
key achievements
thank you so elect um ian did you want
to continue there and then
we'll go to lowry and john yeah very
quick point uh
so michael clark does make very clear in
his comment that um
he very strongly supports uh the work of
julian
assange and the uh because he revealed
uh evidence of criminal behavior by the
u.s
government in its conduct of war and
other matters
so so that's very important and uh
and then he subsequently said what about
uh but what happens when a whistleblower
that gets it wrong which which may be
the case and in fact there has been a
recent case quite an interesting one
that came with analytica scandal
where there were two sort of the initial
whistleblowers chris wiley
who was uh briefly i think director of
search for it and then there was another
whistleblower
who the documentary the great hack was
done on brittany kaiser
uh and they both have very different
versions of events in fact
but uh which is quite interesting
because having you can
sort of compare and contrast there they
both wrote memoirs about it
um but the information commissioner's
office uh i think
uh late last year uh published a report
where basically they said
in fact cambridge analytica didn't work
for the brexit campaign for example
uh that was their finding although
they've been a huge number of
front-page uh sort of stories
about cambridge analytica's role in
brexit the
the uk information commissioner's office
found well that wasn't the case
and and you do get uh but i think uh
these
are these are interesting peculiarities
but on the whole the work of
whistleblowers
if you think of the financial crisis of
2007-2008
much of what we know about the financial
crisis came from whistleblowers
um who were whose lives also were
destroyed
as a result of their blowing a whistle
on their companies often they were quite
senior people
uh if you think it's a financial
misconduct uh military misconduct
intelligence uh misconduct edward
snowden's whispering all sorts of
forms of corporate and uh
government misconduct that we now know
of we know of we only know of
but we know the details because of the
worker whistleblowers so
you can't you know it's it's impossible
to
undervalue that huge public service the
public interest whistleblowers provide
to us thanks ian
and over to you lowry now for some
closing comments
larry i'm saying i know i know i've got
it i've got it and yeah so
uh you know how can i wrap up um we we
we are aware i think painfully aware of
the emergence of the national security
state
um the normalization of war the uh
normalization of
conflicts elective conflicts of
aggression
and the um subordinate the
co-option of the press into supporting
these um
but we are aware of the countervailing
tendency and that is the
the um the wider network the the public
the networked individuals that form the
policy
that form civil society realizing that
they retain a role
and they can participate in this
oversight capacity
and and um where there is a concerted
will
to shine the light of transparency on
um the doings that would like prefer to
be done in
back rooms and uh in in the smoky
darkness where they can get away with
all sorts
and that concerted will will bring
things to life
um and you know it's
um we we will continue to fight for
julian assange and i'm confident he will
not be extradited and they will not
win this um uh victory and exert this
chilling effect
um against um the public's uh
involvement in transparency and its
requirements to have transparency
but um you know i always just want to
say to the
you know the powers to be and and to the
media that um
in general that are well i want to use
the analogy of one of the
pioneers of cyberspace um uh john
gilmore
who famously said um the net
the network interprets censorship as
damage
and roots around it and um so if you're
in the press
if you're willing to um take on that
responsibility
then the the network the the internet
will work with you
and if you're not willing to take on
that responsibility we'll work around
you and that's what
wikipedia did and i'll i'll leave with
the uh
words of my revolutionary comrade who
goes by the name of ice tea
in a song that you wrote called ain't a
damn thing changed and he says um
behind me try it you might cause a riot
what the radio won't play the
underground will supply it
for some final comment i i think i'll
i'll close by saying
that uh in 2015
uh soulette hired me to uh
help the greek government write a new
whistleblower protection law
and in my very first trip
that year in a meeting with the minister
of justice
we were speaking in greek and there is
no word
in greek for whistleblower and so
finally the minister said to me what
exactly is this word you keep using
whistleblower so i explained to him what
i meant
and he said ah like a rat or a snitch
and i said no not at all like a rat or a
snitch
and so we had a long conversation and we
came up with
the term sentinel of the public trust
which is a very
pretty word in greek um sentinel of the
public trust
and that's the word that we continue to
use throughout the process
so my my point here is we have a lot of
work to do
a lot of work we can't let up we can't
stop
we have to look we're we're right and
we're the good guys
and so we have to keep the fight up
whether it's in support of julian
or in support of jeremy hammond or in
support of
anonymous or wikileaks as an
organization we have to
we have to keep up the fight
thanks john thank you very much and to
all those of you who um
we hadn't expected to go for 90 minutes
and we've gone for slightly longer than
that thank you for those who've stayed
throughout
uh we haven't had a single drop in
viewing um but
also um you know the free the truth
events were intended to bring people
like
sullette john and lowry to uh
to the public to allow us to hear and
understand
what's really going on in the world and
to look beyond the
superficial narratives that are spun in
in
some of the media and to look to
understand what true journalism true is
for blowing in the true public interest
is about and we will
continue to have these events the next
event is
likely to be about guantanamo um it's a
it's a rishi yield event which was going
to mark um 19 years
of uh guantanamo being open um
and so that's going to um take place
next and
um i urge you to please follow us follow
the don't extradite assange page please
support stella's campaign to raise funds
for the
um for the defense of julian and uh
first
also a big thank you to gareth pierce
and those at burnburg pierce who are
and in the other legal teams including
um at darty street and elsewhere who are
doing a huge amount of work
um not at the extraordinary rates that
some of these people charge but
at very reasonable rates in order to be
able to push forward this case and
who've been working day and night to get
julian released we are behind you
we support you and uh we hope to see
julian amongst us and perhaps speaking
on
at one of the free the truth panels very
soon
and uh on that note thank you to all our
speakers
and to the committee to defend julian
assange who helped uh fund this zoom
to our technical experts and to our um
to the
i i hesitate to call them this with
media partners we're
actually retweeting and sharing the
information
to all of you who are viewing and have
supported these events
and we look forward to having many more
such discussions thank you
bye bye